A Guide to the Adalbert J. Volck Collection of Etchings, 1861-1865, 1878, 1890, 1912, 1917, 1931, 1933-1934, 1939, 1944-1945, 1949, 1953-1954, 1958, 1962, 1967, 1970, 1978-1979, undated
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Adalbert J. Volck Collection of Etchings 1861-1865, 1878, 1890, 1912, 1917, 1931, 1933-1934, 1939, 1944-1945, 1949, 1953-1954, 1958, 1962, 1967, 1970, 1978-1979, undated
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 149
1 linear foot.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased by the Department in 1979.
Biographical Information
Adalbert J. Volck was born on April 14, 1828 in Augsburg, Bavaria. He studied in Nurnberg and Munich, but was forced to leave the country in 1848 due to his revolutionary sympathies. Volck came to the United States in 1849 and became caught up in the gold rush. By 1851, he had enrolled in the Baltimore College of Dental Surgery, receiving his D.D.S the following year. Volck was a charter member of the Maryland State Dental Association and a founder of the Association of Dental Surgeons. He was instrumental during the Civil War in getting medical supplies to the South.
During the war, Volck made a series of caricatures favorable to the South under the pseudonym of V. Blada. The Confederate War Etchings, the best known of this series, are in the Volck Collection. After the war, Volck became interested in others fields of art. Several of his works can be seen here in Richmond, at the Valentine Museum (portrait of Lee) and the Confederate Museum (shield). Volck died in March, 1912 at the age of 84.
Scope and Content
The Volck Collection is comprised of 29 Confederate War Etchings and three folders containing articles about the artist and his work. Also included is an original first edition of "The Grasshopper", a cantata written by a Virginian, Innes Randolph, and illustrated by Volck.
Arrangement
The etchings are arranged according to their index numbers, 1 through 29. The folders in box 3 are arranged alphabetically.
Contents List
- Index to Confederate War Etchings (Box 1)
- Etching 1. Worship of the North (Box-item 1:1)
- Etching 2. Passage through Baltimore (Box-item 1:2)
- Etching 3. Writing the Emancipation Proclamation (Box-item 1:3)
- Etching 4. Battle in Baltimore, April 19th, 1861 (Box-item 1:4)
- Etching 5. Searching for Arms (Box-item 1:5)
- Etching 6. Enlistment of Sickles' Brigade, N.Y. (Box-item 1:6)
- Etching 7. Buying a Substitute in the North during the War (Box-item 1:7)
- Etching 8. Marylanders Crossing the Potomac to Join the Southern Army (Box-item 1:8)
- Etching 9. Election in Baltimore, November, 1862 (Box-item 1:9)
- Etching 10. Stone Blockade off Charleston, S.C. (Box-item 1:10)
- Etching 11. Making Clothes for the Boys in the Army (Box-item 1:11)
- Etching 12. Slaves Concealing their Master from a Search Party (Box-item 1:12)
- Etching 13. Return of a Raiding Party from Pennsylvania (Box-item 1:13)
- Etching 14. Valiant Men "Dat Fite Mit Siegel" (Box-item 1:14)
- Etching 15. Tracks of the Armies (Box-item 1:15)
- Etching 16. Formation of Guerrilla Bands (Box-item 2:16)
- Etching 17. Jamison's Jayhawkers (Box-item 2:17)
- Etching 18. Smuggling Medicines into the South (Box-item 2:18)
- Etching 19. Offering of Bells to be Cast into Cannon (Box-item 2:19)
- Etching 20. Albert S. Johnston Crossing the Desert to Join the Southern Army (Box-item 2:20)
- Etching 21. Gen'l Stuart's Raid to the White House (Box-item 2:21)
- Etching 22. Gen'l Stuart's Return from Pennsylvania (Box-item 2:22)
- Etching 23. Butler's Victims of Fort St. Philip (Box-item 2:23)
- Etching 24. Prayer in Stonewall Jackson's Camp (Box-item 2:24)
- Etching 25. Counterfeit Confederate Notes Publicly Offered for Sale in the "City of Brotherly Love" (Box-item 2:25)
- Etching 26. Free Negroes in the North (Box-item 2:26)
- Etching 27. Free Negroes in Hayti (Box-item 2:27)
- Etching 28. Cave Life in Vicksburg during the Siege (Box-item 2:28)
- Etching 29. Vicksburg Canal (Box-item 2:29)
- Volck, Adalbert - Related articles 1890, 1912, 1917, 1931, 1933-1934, 1939, 1944-1945, 1949, 1953-1954, 1958, 1962, 1967, 1970, 1979, unknown (Box-folder 3:1)
- Volck, Adalbert - Related correspondence 1864, 1979 (Box-folder 3:2)
- Volck, Adalbert - Related publications 1878, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 3:3)